I am Elisabeth Clapés, psychologist and
content creator and writer
until you like me and I love you
Hello Elisabeth Hello My name is
Isabel, I am the director of human resources.
and mother of two children aged 18 and 15
enchanted today more than ever we know what
It is important to know what we do
we want and we don't but many times we
causes anxiety and worry How
we can manage this anxiety in the face of
situations that overwhelm us, I believe
that the main thing is to understand that the
Anxiety is the alarm but not the
fire in the sense that in many
Occasionally it comes to tell us something
how can something not be right
that there is a job that is waiting for us
affecting us for the worse
relating to someone who is not with us
generating discomfort that there is a decision
that we have to take and we are not able to
anything that our body gives us
is trying to say that he is not
doing harm and as I always say
the body speaks and if you don't listen to it
He screams and if you don't pay attention to him he will scream
so strong that it won't go away, it won't leave you
Listen to something else then first thing
is to pay attention to what is happening to us
saying our body And why yes
It is true that there are many occasions
in which we feel bad we are
sad we have anxiety about situations
that we cannot change and it is that sometimes
life gets very ugly sometimes
It gets very ugly and as a psychologist I have
I have seen many cases of people who
that I have thought my God what is
This person is living It is that it is
impossible to ask if your body doesn't listen to you
see what he says Well what does he say to me
He says I feel bad, he tells me that
I'm sad, he tells me what happened to me
something horrible
that no I can't do anything then yes
It is true that sometimes life happens
things and mothers who lose a child eh
men who are widowed in a manner
unexpected illnesses sometimes life
It leaves you out of the game Listen to your body
because maybe he needs you to stop that
you recover and dedicate time to yourself
that you ask for professional help but more
beyond these situations that I believe
that we have all experienced them I believe that
If we look back we will all remember a
moment in our life that has a date
and time and that is there marked moment in
which we think I'm not going to get out of this and
we went out and we are here then it is
important to remember that we have all
been through situations of not being like this
I go out I remember when I was 13
years that my father committed suicide and when my
family had to give me this news
Of course, giving such news to a girl
13 years old who has been his father all his life
It is something very complicated, I remember that
At that moment I thought it was over, there is no
nothing after this If life has me
taken away from my father after this
I refuse to think that I will continue
living I didn't see it I didn't see anything else And
Look, some bad things have happened to me in the
life but it is such a strong blow that
You couldn't come to me at that moment
say these panic attacks these
anxiety attacks this depression that
you're going to have Listen to your body to see what
He asks you to be resilient, you will come out better.
Since then, no one could stop me from doing this.
come to say that then you have to
admit and understand that there is
situations in life that leave you
offside but you also have to
learn to look back and realize
that we have all experienced situations
so some more, others less, others almost
none and others suddenly 15 of these
situations but once Ah you look back
and you realize that yes In a moment
You thought you wouldn't be able to get out but
you came out I think you realize that the
Being human is wonderful in my opinion
as a psychologist, as a professional and as
As a person I have been able to see that being
human is resilient Dee incredible is
incredible I have seen people
recover from situations that seemed
impossible and they do it but beyond
the situations that we cannot change and
that happen to us and that's it and we survive
how we can and from which we get out
you drag there are situations that do exist
situations that are worth listening to
to our body and tell us what's wrong with me
Why do I have anxiety? Why do I get anxious every time?
that I'm going to work before entering the
I feel bad at work because when
the holidays end in the last few days
three days of vacation I start to have
tachycardia I start to feel like
cry because my body is
Saying this, I go to work and
Then when I get home I feel relief
but at night again I know that by the
Tomorrow when I wake up I have to
return to this job site or why
I was happy before I met this
person since this person forms
part of my life I'm not well I have
anxiety I have insecurities I have arrived
to ask myself things I never thought I would
I would ask myself what doesn't fit me
I am behaving in a way that is not
represents me then it's worth it
pay attention to what our body
tells us and above all respect him because
If you listen to it and do nothing about it
Respect is of no use but you have to be a
not very brave at times and make decisions
that maybe you don't feel like doing at the moment
but your body is asking you for it
Please shout that you take us all
We have felt guilty about things that
we have done or even said that we have
stopped doing or saying what to us
can teach guilt and mistakes
guilt teaches us
responsibility the responsibility of not
make the same mistakes again but
I think we all carry the blame for
Something is okay, nothing is wrong, everyone
We will have nights that we have lengthened without
sleep until the wee hours of the morning
thinking about what we said that time
day what others must have thought
When we said what has How has
affected the image that these had
people of us and we are sometimes
turning them in an even manner
obsessive about little things we did ago
time No and like the others
they took it but the others are
busy with the same thing thinking about
little things they did in their day and how
the rest of us take this in the end
This is life This is what it is no no no
you don't live with an instruction manual
you put your foot in it, you screw up and you have to be
Brave and responsible as to
admit it not to repeat it because
that's what apologizing is all about
repent not to repeat it again if you
Hey, you apologize for a mistake you made.
committed and you commit it again you are
manipulating the other person Then
If you have made a mistake, what you have
what to do is take responsibility
assume not not throw it out assume that
you have made him accept it and apologize
if the other person accepts your apology
great but if you don't accept them that's fine too
You're going to have to respect it, it doesn't have to
What to forgive you I remember a friend
mine who was unfaithful to his partner and they had
6 years have passed and he Every time he counted
This infidelity cried, cried not of
overwhelming way but it is
Tears fell and he said no no
She forgave me but I can't.
Yes, I forgive myself but I can't.
I can't talk about this topic
this topic without me falling One
tear for the pain I caused to this
person seems precious to me it seems
wonderful that you remember with pain
the pain that you caused that obviously
does not prevent you from leading a functional life
but mistakes are there for that
let us take responsibility and not
let us repeat it obviously
But well, yes, we do feel the pain that
we have caused then there is another type of
guilt that I carry a lot and that I see
a lot in patients and it is the fault
for having endured something is no longer
the blame for what I have done but for
what I have allowed to be done to me
Okay, this guilt weighs heavily.
when we are linked to a person
that a friend, a family or someone hurts us
be it a family member, a friend, a partner
especially a couple I as a therapist
as a couple it's what I see the most and this one
person mistreats us and we
we try to leave the skin in which we
stop mistreating to show this
person that we are valid
valid enough for
He treated us well and we spent years
accepting accepting in quotation marks no
humiliations, vexations, lack of
respect we feel sorry for the other
We feel guilty about a lot of things that
They make us stay in that relationship
but when we get out of it and the pain
guilt the feeling of responsibility
fear and these blocking emotions
They are no longer with us, a phrase arises that
I listen a lot to my patients, which is
how could I let them do that to me and it's
horrible and it weighs a lot, it weighs a lot
because everything you allow between
quotation marks mean everything you allow
that you
do affects your self-esteem and your
self-concept and it eats you up from the inside
because when they hurt another
person we jump not the How do you allow that
do this to you How is it in fact the
society punishes the victim a lot and
He says, well, it's because you allowed it.
that you did not set limits is that you
you have stopped in fact I heard one
victim of gender violence who
he said that a one
friend told him that the first one was the first one
The slap his partner gave him was his fault
of his partner for being an abuser but the
second of it was her fault for being stupid and
You say, wow, how is this not going to load?
person guilty of having tolerated
but we are all susceptible to
to be mistreated or to be mistreated or
that they don't treat us with respect
saying no one is born with an armor that
protects from everything yes it is true that there is
personalities that may have more
tendency to tolerate more submissive people
and so on But I always say that if not
you have been mistreated is because the person
that you had to skip all of them. Ah, all of you
your entire safety net to get
reach inside you and from within
get infected you have not met her you have not
suffered that because you have not met
the right person who has disabled
all your alarms so that you don't jump
none and once was inside you
boom It's like saying
Ah well how could you allow it?
catch that cold, that catarrh. Good.
My immune system is not the same as the
yours but your immune system is not immune
to everything is immune to certain things Well it is
the same when you have not been mistreated
It's because you haven't found the right person.
adequate adequate incorrect actually
incorrect No then I think it is
It is essential to understand that the person who
safer in the sense that the
person who is least likely to
being mistreated is someone who has already experienced it
has learned and will detect with more
ease but it is very bad that we are
fill your mouth saying how you have
allowed when there are actually so many
people in the world who think that
none of them can finish you off
be very foolish Elizabeth in your book
You say that traumatic events do not
They always help us evolve to what
You mean with this statement because a
a little
to what has been sold a lot today
Well, to this day, nothing has happened.
sold a lot this you can do it all
thanks to what happened to you, you are who you are
Hey, you're going to learn a lot from this.
It has happened Yes I have learned but I
I was happier before when I didn't
I had no idea then it seems like a
disrespectful to sell people the
fact that good as they have lived is
tremendous misfortune now they are going to be a
best version of themselves because maybe not
maybe they spend their whole lives trying
rebuild as humanly possible
then you have to go very delicately
and especially in Mental Health that we see
many patients with very serious situations
We psychologists don't see ourselves as delicate.
that we see these patients that
we try and connect with them no
see you in the power to come
With these stories I do not then consider
important whenever we see that
Tell us about someone who has experienced this
something something hard something painful respect the
process of this person understanding that the
is going through a bad time and you are not going to force her to
learn you will mature you will be better
person after this no But yes that
It is true that beyond the
realism life is what it is to everyone
Terrible things happen to us, some more
terrible than others but in the end I
I always say that when we get to the
world we are a blank canvas Okay and
the rest of the people around us
the events that happen to us
they are painting that Canvas and when
we finish our life we can look at it
with perspective and see how it has happened to us
the table has been left in terms of the
strokes of this painting We are from
one way or another we have traces that
painful strokes that make us cry
strokes that provoke us a lot of anger
strokes that make each of us happy
has his picture not with those strokes that
They hurt, what can we do? We spend all our time
life contemplating it at the time of
look at our chart to see what it is
general picture we can spend our lives
looking at those ugly lines, those lines that
they have hurt us but we remain stuck
It won't be of any use there in the end.
painting is a complete painting with what
good with the bad and with what most or
less is better then we have to cross out the stones
There is no need to underline them in highlighter
that they are the center of our life and
every time we have a conversation
let's talk about that bad thing that we
It happened and we went into a loop over and over again
time and let's not have another topic of
conversation that will help us
find to find us better not me
What I say should be done with them
strokes that hurt are to go around them
identify them, know that they are there and
say yes I went through this I went through it
tremendously bad there are times that I still feel
It hurts even today I am like this
I react this way and I have this
way to link me this way of
answer because I have lived this but
Apart from this I have a huge painting and
I'm going to pay attention to the Canvas
complete we all feel anger hate
sadness envy what can we do with
These emotions we all feel emotions
unpleasant the difference is in what
we do with them because I am
psychologist and I feel envy I feel jealous
I feel sadness and I feel anger just like
everyone but the difference is in
that I'm not going to allow this to happen to me
kidnap these emotions from me
kidnap me and make a monster out of me
Because we all have a monster inside
that you can eat someone but not
we can allow this to come out no
we can allow everything that
We are sorry that it is unpleasant to finish it.
paying the others then you are
emotions must be managed but
manage when I say manage the
Patients tell me Yes of course as if
It was not easy, it is not easy, but it is that
If you try to manage him when he is
up here most likely not
you can manage your emotions at all
They are a wave that gives a rush when they arrive
to the highest part and then tend to the
always down In fact that's why when
we are very angry or we are very
sad and then it happens we say Well the same
It wasn't that bad, because I still saw it.
because she was very angry But maybe the
another person no no no I have not paid it I have
paid with him and it's not fair not this to us
has happened to everyone from looking back and
to say what a kidnapping is what it amounts to
an amygdalar hijacking of emotions
They can eat me, okay then no
I am able to think rationally.
Therefore at that moment you have to
stop for a moment, excuse the redundancy
to become aware of what is happening
what is happening to our body because
I'm very heavy on the subject of
listen to your body and what it is
passing inside it because it doesn't
you can control at that moment and
You don't have to try to control it either
So I always tell my patients
I say talk to yourself in a way
informal listen to yourself and tell yourself aunt you are
you're getting extremely nervous
getting very angry and if we continue for
here and allow yourself the luxury of responding
to the other person just as you are
feeling you are going to hurt the other and
then you'll have to ask him
apologies and you're also going to have to
forgive yourself for what you have
done or said therefore respect yourself and
love yourself enough to put
a limit at that moment and not allow yourself
eat the other person that that
Little monster that we all carry inside, no
eat the other person because you want to
It is also preventing the bad part
that we all carry eats the person
which we want then after
This kidnapping we will take the
decisions that we have to make
but they will be much more rational and I
I think it is also important to keep in mind
realize that you have to be smart
How many of us have acted with
the emotional high and then we have
said my goodness, what a mess I've made even
There are times when you are on that high and
You know you're not entirely right.
with what you are arguing You know
that it's getting out of hand but
yet you are so angry that you leave it
go there is something inside you that tells you
Come on, continue with the drama but no
It's really not smart to do this.
because you are harming yourself you are
harming the other and then you will have
to apologize as I said and
Forgive yourself because that also exists
forgive yourself he oysters I have
spent half a lifetime because this doesn't usually happen
being a single occasion is usually a pattern
of behavior a pattern of response
constant not until I learned
to respect that rise and work on it
work on responding on the way down
He acted this way, not like me.
the others When I get angry then
I consider it essential that there be a
moment in our life in which we
let's stop and say this way of acting
It doesn't represent me and above all I don't want it
that represents me therefore when I
It feels like this. So I'm going to allow myself to feel it.
because I'm not going to repress it, I'm not going to
control I'm just going to leave it
pass because I respect myself enough
to act intelligently and
knowing that the right decisions are
I'm going to take it later because I don't
It is appropriate to do it now and as I respect myself
I'm going to decide what's best for me because
live
It's okay. We've all had a streak.
of our life in which we have not been
the ideal person nor the healthy person and
We have all been able to be the toxic one in the
someone's life is impossible to be the
Well, of all the stories you tell
and if you are the good one of all
stories you tell you have a problem
and you are deceiving yourself
then you have to know how to forgive that
phase that stage that part of
we that it was not at all good that
It was not right to apologize as I have
said to whoever deserves it and forgive us
we because we have to understand
that we were not born knowing that
misfortune at school This is not our fault
He explained that each one comes from his father and
from his mother and that no matter how much he
try to do well and the best you can
Sometimes, without wanting to, not everything turns out as it should.
Well, as we want, my mother told me
Poor me when I stayed
pregnant with you I read all the books
that there was about motherhood and education
respectful because I wanted you to have
a life as stable as possible, peaceful and healthy
possible but everything went wrong
and everything was a disaster and when you arrived
to adolescence that was was was
tremendous because I was good I had one
very complicated life Not even today
I am aware that my parents
They did what they could humanly. But
That is not always enough, that is why there is
that self-educate to forgive that part of
you who didn't know everything you know
everything you currently know and
keep going and let go of that I'm not proud of
from that stage but I'm going to be
proud of everything that I am from here
from now on all this taking of
consciousness most of us want it in
our adult life And if I think like the
my teenage children live there must be
confusing and overwhelming what can we do
from the family to help them
manage emotions better yes by
misfortune This is something that is learned
when you are an adult because you learn to
of blows More than anything because in the
school doesn't teach it I don't know good
Currently there are schools that
They are introducing the topic quite a bit
emotional education but generally
It is not something that is
in very normalized no then
Unfortunately we have that
lack as parents but the
Teenagers have another disadvantage
and it's the rush and the hormonal flurry of
the age and that perhaps their parents do not
They are the people who go to the most
listen because teenagers
They listen more to their peer group
friends no but I think there always are
to work on a father-son bond
from respect, respect your space
As a teenager I am here as a
safe place but I want to convey to you eh
how important it is that you ask yourself
the things that you question
Teenagers spend years copying
influencer who likes dressing like
the cool friend of the group repeating the
words that a boy in class said
And now the teacher says this, I think about it.
But the other day Pepe told me something else.
and I do too, in the end they let themselves go
from what you hear and I think it is
It is essential to teach a teenager to
have self-criticism to question oneself
ask yourself what to do
introspection to say Okay, what's wrong with me?
how do I find where this error hurts
that I have committed I have repeated more times
These are patterns that repeat themselves in me.
These are things I do frequently and
the harm that others are doing to me
I really think I deserve that
Because this friend got angry with me
Okay, but I'm going to sit down for a moment.
place of acting in this kidnapping amalar
I'm going to sit down and try to think
what has he done what have I done how do I know
He may have felt how I have
sense I and what opinion do I have about it
Regarding adolescents, we must
teach them to draw conclusions but by
your own foot i.e. conclusions
They have to be taught to
question and do
introspection what is good about me
What do I want in my life? What kind of
person I want to be in my life
because teenagers have a
medley of friends who have nothing to
see that perhaps they do not contribute anything to them
They hurt each other, one gets along well
but the other treats him terribly, the other treats him
leaves aside the other for the other makes him
the emptiness in class and you say but why
You get along well with people who make you
damage because no one has taught him to
select and this happens to him but we
It happens to us as adults who then
We grow up and say, wow, what a mess
because I am surrounded by people who
Half of them don't give me anything and you leave
being left without friends in adulthood and
You say I'm running out of friends, right?
that in adolescence they did not filter more
young No
filterability
but we started to filter we started to
choosing our peace of mind we begin to
realize that who treats me
Whoever treats me well one day does not have to
what to be my best friend because this The
Teenagers is a I get along with him
My best friend, I get along well with that one
Well then there is also a discussion
but we fixed it does something terrible to me
It doesn't matter, I forgive teenagers.
We must teach them to set limits
also so that it doesn't arrive so late
in adulthood but I am also very
in favor of giving them some freedom
that they make mistakes and not be doing them wrong
the way for them to go there
In the end, we have all been teenagers and
We have all learned it is necessary but
if we learn from introspection
Much better Elisabeth, you say that
Emotions are reactions that
represent how we adapt to what
external can you explain a little more to me
on this reflection the emotions are
what happens inside us in
depending on what happens outside
We are worth it and I think it is important
keep in mind that they do not always go
fully adjusted for that reason we have
spoken of amygdalar hijacking no but
Yes, it is true that sometimes you have to
stand up and say okay regardless
Of all this that I'm feeling, what is it?
the objective reality of what is
happening for example My partner is
talking to a girl is happening
nothing serious but I can feel jealous
and I can go and raise hell or I can
wait for my partner to come and ride him
a chicken or I can stop talking to him and
punish him for something that bothers me
state and here I think there is an error and it is
that emotions are wonderful and we
They indicate many things sometimes of the
outside and sometimes inside not in
This case would be that they tell us something about the
inside that we don't feel completely
secure in the relationship either by
our attachment Whether through experiences
past but they come to tell us something There is
that you listen to them but you don't always have to
act accordingly when I
I understand what is happening
outside is not the reality of how I am
perceiving
I understand that this reaction is in me
well I'm feeling jealous I'm getting
feeling insecure But that's not going to work for me
attacking my partner is not going to happen to me
make go look for validation in the
person from outside who tells me no that
nothing was happening that I didn't tell you
I'm being unfaithful that I was just
talking to her about work I don't
I need that because he and I see it
We see that reality himself, he is
talking to a girl I don't have to
why get angry That's why it's okay then it is
important that we feel it as it is not
Let's go to the other to find an answer to what
that I have felt, that is to say if I have felt it
sense I look for an answer in myself and if I see
that is causing me a lot of discomfort
We are also going to normalize telling
our couple after Look honey I have
angry about something I knew I wasn't
I had the right to be angry about that, don't you
I said nothing at the time but I have
insecure sense in this in this
moment when I saw you talking to
This girl, don't worry, I'll get it.
I realized that it was not normal but
I wanted to pass it on to you so that you
you knew why we are a couple and
I want to share it with you then yes
that I consider important
be validated and interpreted appropriately
Beyond everything we feel,
exterior to also be able to be
aware when there are people from outside
that try to make us feel like
certain small ways
mistreated, that is to say if we are always
looking for validations outside in what
They tell us others are going to manipulate us
because on many occasions we are going to
find people who turn our heads
tortilla then pause everything
think okay, I who am seeing and I who
I understand. And from here on, what am I going to do?
interpret because there are people who
They make you feel small, so if you look for
validation in a good person
great but if you look for it in the person
wrong that you have to have a
axis within you immovable Good
immovable neither but almost
immovable that I tell you this yes this no
You tolerate this, you don't stop thinking and
how you interpret the outside no
because if you don't have that and you look for it
Outside you will find good ones and you
you will meet bad people and if
you meet bad ones and how
You interpret the exterior. It depends on what
What do the others tell you? We'll see each other.
in situations like for example he knows
that he has been unfaithful to me, let's imagine that
I really do know that he has been unfaithful to me
but as you tell me no as you do
You say I'm crazy, that I've lost the
sanity that I am not right that they are
my imaginations Well, well, as I
I'm going to believe it but no
I have an axis within me and what I
I see what I live, what I experience, I see it
I think because I value the outside with my
criterion my criterion is valid There is
people who make us feel small
There are people who make us feel bad and
sometimes we are not very we are not capable of
understand Why I don't know if you will have
ever happened not that you are with
someone whether it be a boss, a family member or
friend or partner even and when you are
with that person regardless of what
let it be the outside you feel
small you feel below that
person and you are human beings the same
But automatically that person appears
and there is an aura that passes you by, you pass by
from normal size to dried
with a dryer like this you stay small
does not make small and here I always them
I tell my patients that what you
a person transmits the vibe that he gives you
One person is enough for
you make a decision and then from
out there from there we see what
we do but to get you away from one
A person is just enough with how he makes you feel and
I always give the example of the
glass ceramic if the glass fire
it's on and I put my hand when
I'm burning myself, I'll move my hand away, okay then
what a person transmits to us is
for Exactly the same you if you
you burn, you don't put your hand, you are
burning and you say I'm going to see if it really
I'm burning maybe it's me who's
crazy and that I'm playing the
reality in a way that is not Maybe
I'm not burning much maybe not
It hurts so much maybe I'm exaggerating or
The hob may not be on and
be no you take your hand away and then already
see if the hob is on and the
you pay for the vibe that it transmits to you
a person is the same to me you are
you are making me feel uneasy
feel small you are me there is something of you
that it's not making me feel good
I'm not going to stay here and see what if I
I'm crazy. Yes, I'm exaggerating, huh?
Not because I have something inside me in
what I trust completely and is how I
makes me feel my surroundings And if you make me
feel bad I'm going to walk away and then
With perspective I will decide why
From here out they look much better
things Then when I can take
perspective and is far away I will see if it is
which has really been an interpretation
mine if it really can be that
I may have exaggerated if at that time
I had a bad day and that's why I
I took your comment the wrong way. But first things first.
It's all that I'm going to pay attention to.
because I am important enough
and because I am worth enough and
because I know myself as a person and I know how
I am and if you make me feel bad it's because
something happens then I'm not going to stay
wait for you to destroy me so that
then I already have feaci evidence
presents that you were going to hurt me
but directly to the one that makes me
feel like this I walk away there is one there is a
experiment that was done in the
Stanford University which I love
that Zimbardo did and that is that he took
Well, a group of people made it
mentally stable young people with everyone
more or less the same variables and
He separated it into two groups
okay in one of the basements of the
part of psychology at the University of
Stanford was transformed into a prison
and they put them there and said half
They are guards and half are prisoners
Let's see what happens, it was fake, they were paid
what was at that time 15 for what
so much no there was no great remuneration
But but well there was a little one
incentive What happens that What happened
happened
that despite being an experiment and those who
were taking part in the experiment
knowing it by being aware of them
The prisoners began to act
as prisoners and the guards began
to act as guards punishing the
prisoners having their mattress taken away
taking off their blankets making them
walk around naked in prison
humiliating themselves when they were people
equals and the prisoners developed
emotional disorders for this But for
What if they had been put there in the end?
in an experiment because sometimes there are
people who position themselves above
you and this bias of authority you have it
Do you think there are people who put themselves on a pedestal?
and it seems that you have to respect the
pedestal on which they have climbed
But it is not like that, that is why it is very important
that you have an axis inside that you
help you validate what's out there and
saying is worth very well in the case of
Stanford experiment I'm in a
experiment
and this no matter how much I am a guard that
I have to because the only indication
that was given to you is that you have to keep the
order in the in the in the mock prison
obviously and being all aware of
that was fake, they gave me this
as much as I see that my colleagues
are exercising violence on the
prisoners I know what reality is and
therefore I make decisions for myself
because if it can't happen as well
In another experiment they did that
He did Milgram and it was because of pressure from
public was able to make the subject that
was on stage giving shocks
electric shock to another person under pressure
the rest are obviously worth it
electric shocks were faked
everything was set up but the guy who
the the eh that pressed the button
the downloads were not a person
totally normal and due to pressure it was
able to think that that was
the right thing because that is important to have
an axis within you because if not what
What happens outside will end up changing how
you act the social tests play a
very important role in the daily life of
Our children connect with each other there
appearances influences and stimuli of
all kinds you are a very active person
on Instagram uploading very useful content
on psychology for the new
generations How can they be used?
networks without obsessing And what can we
making parents respectful is what it is
It is true that social networks are a
double-edged sword and I have been in the
two sides because I have been a user
social media consumer person
that was compared with all the
ideal relationships that I saw on social media
social thinking Jo I will never have
something like that Or what I have is not known
seems not and then been on the other side
on the side of the person who
publishes his life on social networks and
receives admiration from the
Besides, there was a time when I climbed higher
eh about my personal life and about everything
about my relationship because
I try to expose the person who gives me
authorization to expose my then
friends and others did not share them
I shared my relationship and saw
responses from very young girls and no
so young telling me I want a boyfriend
I'll never have one like yours.
relationship like this your relationship is perfect
You are perfect and while I was reading those
messages there were days that I had just
argue with my partner and I was done
dust and I read them and thought my God
What a great deception What a great deception But I
I don't have to expose those either
discussions in front of everyone
because on the one hand you learn that there is
people who are even happy and for another it is
my personal life and I don't want to expose it
not that part of my life but it's true
that I have lived both sides and by living
the two faces I have realized that
What is on social networks is not even a
20% of what we see that we expose
beautiful now teenagers have to
To convey this to you, I am only exposing the
good part of my life when I expose the
bad part I do it with things that
I feel comfortable exposing myself
Nervous because I have an interview.
This has happened to me with the car but
I don't expose, I have argued with my partner
we have family problems, we don't
we agree with this we have had
I am facing a tremendous crisis
the relationship I do not expose this but
It happens, but it happens like it happens to us all.
So it is important to me and
convey to teenagers that I have
been on both sides and from this
On the other hand I greatly admired what I saw in
social networks and from this I tell you that
It wasn't true and I was wrong at all
no life is as perfect as it seems
and we have to take the liberty of
stop following those accounts that we
They generate discomfort. There was a time when I
life in which I wanted Well, let's go to the
gym and wanted to have a more
according to the canons of beauty and me
I was obsessing over certain models
that they had bodies that I
would never reach mainly because
They are two heads taller than me and the growth
I can't change it but I suffered
when I saw those photos, those bodies and
There was a day when I said what the heck
unfollow man she can
Upload the photos you want and for real
You are beautiful and wonderful But I am not
I can see you every day
because it does not do me any good because in
At this moment in my life I don't feel
well with my body because if I don't
I feel good about my body, I can't see
as you are exposing to me what I do not
I can have and apparently they have both
been So if we are going through a
complicated moment at the family level
maybe follow influencers who are
exposing their married life with their
children, their parents and everything ideal and perfect
It is not what will suit us in that
moment Then maybe these accounts
we stopped following and when we
we find better we can resume or if
you are very bad with your partner do not continue
the couple that seems perfect on social media
social because you are self
deceiving yourself you will be deceiving them
They're not doing it to hurt you. And
This is important to keep in mind
because then you open the posts of
the influencers And you see an insurance that it
You're going to leave all that now, it's a lie
This is not necessary either, we must also
manage emotions a little
unpleasant so that they don't eat them
others as we have said before but
let's take the liberty of unfollowing
to someone because it makes us uncomfortable and
beyond unfollowing someone
that makes us uncomfortable which is very
also lawful
you have to do introspection and say okay
Why does this person make me feel uncomfortable?
What does this person have?
This person projects that he is projecting to me
doing harm because this is the world
digital great wonderful But then
I have my life and in my life those
insecurities that are awakening in me
This person who is emphasizing to me that
It's reminding me that they will continue
affecting because what I see on networks
I also see it in real life.
In real life there are beautiful couples of
friends that I'm going to see and well maybe
They also make me insecure, no
then you also have to work on that
part of saying okay you you or whoever me
You have helped me realize one thing
insecurity that I'm not going to spit out
I'm not going to attack you on social media.
social for that reason I'm going to leave you
continue for my well-being but apart from
That for my well-being I will also
explore and I'm going to address these
insecurities that you generate in me or that you
that these insecurities with my body
These insecurities with my relationship
I think it's also good that sometimes
we question our own
life instead of saying hey look sorry
I'm jealous because I'm going to go to this influencer
to give birth for this topic or this
I see the couple as very perfect to me
upset because my relationship is a man
that the sofa is not lifted all day and
don't give me a rose on St. Day
Valentin, well, I'm going to start criticizing.
This relationship does not take me away from what I
It hurts and I do an introspection.
What makes me feel bad, what's in me?
life that I don't like and that I should
change Or maybe not to change but
accept accept yourself as you are because
I haven't changed since I saw those
influences that I liked so much
bodies I am the same person but I have
learned to value myself as I am
love me as I am and understand that
She has a beautiful body I have
another beautiful body because both
bodies allow us to lead a life
healthy and exercise and play and
laugh and make love and be with
friends all this Then it is yes I leave you
to continue But I also work for myself
see where that lack is that has me
the fact that you make me feel bad
Why is it so hard for us to be alone and
enjoy our own company and
On the other hand, what can we do to
foster this attitude in our children
Since we were little it was difficult for us because it was something
what we have not been taught in the end
When we go to school we are taught
to socialize with our colleagues
made the school in part is for
teach us to be active members of the
society and above all to interact with
Others, the family, also take us with them
family friends who have children of
Our age teaches us to be in
family to be with friends and with the
time is expected of you to have a
couple a relationship have children too
and in the end everything is very social, we don't know
focuses on a totally social life
well But at no time did we
teaches us to be with ourselves now
introspection into how we are already
meet us Not me when I was little
Sunday mornings my mother told me
I ran a bookstore and we bought a
book for me that week until
the following Sunday he read it to me and it was
beautiful because I went to the bookstore with
all calm and looked through the books of
Kika superwitch or Jerome stilton oliya
the books because those of Jerome
Stilton smells and decides which book
I wanted to spend an hour passing by
pages touching books
smelling it but emptied the shelf and
placed in order in plan This is the
First book I want this week This
This is the next one, this is such that I ordered them
And he said, come on, well, I'm leaving this week.
I'm going to take this one next week.
another because they wouldn't let me buy two
So that moment of choosing a book
for me It was a moment with me it was a
time to question myself what I wanted
read that week about What a Story
I wanted to learn something about What's good at
what was I going to be thinking that week
because my mother gave me that week to
read it to me if I don't read it the following Sunday
I had finished the previous book, I didn't
I could live that moment of going to the
bookstore and look for a new book because
I hadn't finished the one I had
bought last week Then I
How I liked that moment so much
Choosing a book already wakes me up from Monday to
Friday to read it and be able to return to
I think that living it is necessary to instill it in
young people moments like this moments of
choose a book read it pay attention
paint draw meditate even before
Until a few years ago you said you meditated and
you imagined a Buddha was not something normal
normalized and today we talk about
mindfulness and we say good to meditate
be in the present be in the
present activates the parasympathetic system
Scrubbing the floor brings us back to calm
dishes I realize that I get home
I wash the dishes with music when I
I put on a podcast when I drive
I put music on full blast, I sing and when I
I go to bed, put on a series and when
there is absolute silence in my house
because I haven't put anything I feel
uncomfortable
because I have not been taught to be in
silence to wash the dishes and be
noting the temperature of the water
amount of soap I put on the plate
It stays clean or it doesn't stay clean How
place it so that everything doesn't fall and
it breaks on me and I think the children
These moments must be taught to children
children to teenagers but above all
I would emphasize from childhood not to
teach them these moments for them to
putting on is going to seem silly but
choose the soap they like to use
cremita ain quietly without catching
stretches quickly to get to school no
choose the school clothes of the day
previous what do you want to wear tomorrow
see what signatures you have tomorrow
Physical education, well, let's see what you do.
what will make you more comfortable AND
then what jacket are you going to wear
then help the child to have spaces
for him to connect with himself and
to stop living on autopilot
and return a little to the present and to the
calms many of the people who are
In our lives we have not chosen them and
others yes how we can create links
healthy and choose the right people
consciously I consider that
The main thing is to know yourself to know what
needs someone like you, that is to say
someone like me at this moment in my life
life what it needs maybe there was a time
of my life in which I wanted to surround myself
of more active party people
more active more extroverted no And this
It gave me what I wanted
that moment But maybe I am now
at a stage in my life where I want
peace I always say that people
They come with a soundtrack, okay? And there is
times that you want your life to have
the soundtrack of abich or vigeta and
It's what you feel like at that moment but
There are times in life when you want it to
sea enio moricone soundtrack band
then you have to know how to select the
people who know how to make music
you want them to be the soundtrack of
your life at this moment and for that
apart from knowing each other, you have to put
limits because there are people who no matter how much
however good they may be and however much you
want and the ones you want will go to
jump your limits That happens but for
That's what you have to transmit to them
Look at this, it makes me uncomfortable. This makes me
hurt this I don't like this I need this
you change it and someone who loves you one
A good person will accept that you
set limits because if you don't
It means that he benefited from when
you didn't put them on a person who loves you
will not continue doing something that makes you
damage knowing that it can
change it Then it is essential to say
Ok, I know myself, I know what one needs
person like me and people who
I allow myself to be part of my bubble of my
Life is worth it, I have to set limits for them.
to teach them how to treat me too
because maybe I have a friend who
I love it very much but it is very direct to
Sometimes I make some comments.
that they hurt me because I am
sensitive and I can tell you look Marta you
I love you so much but you know what happens to me
that when you answer this way I
you hurt and I would like you to please
you would take into account a little more how I am
I don't then set limits
essential to build an environment
healthy and build a healthy environment too
It involves making a good selection of
Personal life is like your life is like
a company you in your company eh you're not going to
hire anyone who comes first
give a resume inside you won't
make a selection of personnel that
staff selection is also done
With friends you have to select
the people you let form
part of your life because you have to
understand that being part of your life is
a privilege That is to say you are
deciding that someone spends time
with you time that you will not recover
therefore it is a privilege and perhaps
You have not done any kind of work for 6 years.
cleaning staff and you realize
that there are people who no longer
They are on your wavelength that you have evolved
and they don't Or they have evolved
to the other side that you have taken
different paths that you don't like how
have become what they have become and
So I think it's important too
clean up staff to say okay
These people at the time made me
happy but not anymore then there are certain eh
companies I'm going to take from
distance Therefore we could
sum it up a bit in getting to know each other
know what we need to set limits and
do staff cleaning, do not drag
always the same people all your life
because we evolve and our
our relationships have to
evolve with us too What
It happens when someone, even though they are knowledgeable
of our own limits it is crossed
Of course, here comes what is so difficult
to do that is that the limit has
meaning that is to say if I put you a
The limit is so that you don't cross it
But if you skip it
how clear a limit supposes a
consequence if it is not fulfilled and I have
to respect me enough to
make the tough decision that if you
You're skipping them And I've already done it for you
ordered several times unfortunately I
I'm going to unlink from you because if I don't
I am able to carry out the
consequence that I have said would lead to
but if you were to skip that again
I better not set a limit if I
I tell my partner if you cheat on me again
I'm going to leave the relationship but when
She's unfaithful again, I don't let her reach the limit
It hasn't made any sense and
I have simply shown my partner
that my word has no value that neither
not even my my my will has
value therefore the most difficult of the
Limits is to comply with the consequences
that we have said that they would have said
limits therefore Unfortunately and
It can hurt us because eliminating
someone in our life is always
painful though afterwards Eh it can be a
relief I always say there is
Goodbyes that we started crying and
we ended up applauding
But even if it is painful we have to
make the brave decision not to do
what we feel like at that moment because
What we want is not always what we want
good for us and for our lives
and cut ties with those who do not
They respect our limits because
It means as I have commented before that it is
benefit from when we do not put them in
This sense How can we be a
a healthy person for others to be a
A healthy person for others begins with
to know oneself, to know oneself
maybe if I am a very very very person
very very insecure I will not be able to be
the most confident person in the world no but
I think it consists of putting on
realistic goals and decide
I want to be this kind of person
I want to make those around me feel this way.
surround me I want to give this to those who
to those who love me and that's what I'm going to
try to make it worth it imagine that I am
a very insecure person that I am
person who finds it difficult to transmit to
others What you feel for them not for
example then I'm going to make small ones
small steps, small goals
little by little they will bring me closer to
what I want to be I will also be
observe and I will pay close attention
to the response of others because yes
several people complain about the same thing
about me maybe I have to review it no
I am perfect, I have to check if everything
The world tells me that I have a lot
character and that when I get angry I explode
Well maybe I need to review that part.
My being healthy for others consists
also in reviewing myself and saying
Okay, I'm repeating this pattern. I'm going to
to work on it and on the other hand in Towards
where I want to go What kind of person
I want to be what I want to transmit to others
others and I'm going to start getting small
goals to climb are not necessary
that he climbs to the summit in one day because it is
impossible and in fact the changes so
Big goals that we set for ourselves sometimes last
little in time is how I'm going to start
to exercise every day for a
week well then you won't go from 0 to 10
to be able to pass but from c0 to one and from one
to two Yes then it consists of that in
know very well who you want to be and what
that you want to convey to others and
set small goals so you can go
reaching that point I think that
something that a man said is very important
philosopher named Immanuel Kant in
his categorical imperative that was the
The phrase is not exactly like that but
understand the concept of acts of
so that your conduct can be
adopted as a universal law and I
I use it a lot both in consulting and
with myself saying
Okay, if everyone acted like me.
at this very moment what would happen
the world would be better or the world would be worse
be a healthy person for others I think
What happens when we understand that we are in
a community that when we go through the
road and we give way to someone
we are having a gesture with a
person who, although he doesn't tell us, perhaps
He is thanking us for giving us a one.
a good face, a good gesture, a smile
a beautiful word is small shapes
to make the world a little more beautiful
because the world itself is sometimes
ugly ugly tremendous and when we see a video
on Instagram or Facebook of a firefighter
Saving a kitten we say I wish more
There could be more people like that
so in the end he acts in such a way that you
conduct can become law
universal And being a healthy person is no longer
not only for others but for the world
In general, we should apply this a lot.
way of thinking to understand that we live in
a community and act as one
community with a common good that is the
that within the possible between us
let's treat each other as well as we can
Because we all have backpacks that weigh
and burdens and pains and you when you have
someone in front you don't know what is
living that person therefore I know
as kind as you can because the
world is going well or the part of the world that
It's going well, it's going well thanks to people like that and
No, on the contrary, Elisabeth has me
I loved the interview, I loved it
meet you Thank you very much, thank you to you
It's been a pleasure to be here
[Music]
with you an